Inventory of the Sheldon H. Harris Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Sheldon H. Harris Papers
1942-2002
2004C40
Harris, Sheldon H.
53 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes. (22 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings, correspondence, photocopies of government documents, photographs, sound recordings, video tapes, and printed matter, of an American historian relating mainly to biological warfare, especially as conducted by Japan in China before and during World War II. Includes research material used in the preparation of the book by S. H. Harris, Factories of Death: Japanese Biological Warfare, 1932-1945, and the American Cover-up (London, 1994).
Administrative Information
Access
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2004
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1928 August 22 Born, Brooklyn, New York
1949 A.B. (cum laude), Brooklyn College (now Brooklyn College of the City University of New York)
1950 A.M., Harvard University
1955 Married Sheila J. Black
1957-1958 Instructor in history, Brooklyn College (now Brooklyn College of the City University of New York)
1958 Ph.D., Columbia University, New York
1958-1963 Associate professor of social science, Bradford Durfee College of Technology (now Southeastern Massachusetts University), Bradford, Massachusetts
1962 Recipient, Roger Benjamin Foundation Award
1963-1964 Recipient, American Council of Learned Societies research grant
1963-1966 Assistant professor, California State University, Northridge
1966 Visiting professor, University of California, Los Angeles
1966-1969 Associate professor, California State University, Northridge
1969-1991 Professor of history, California State University, Northridge
1971 Recipient, American Philosophical Society grant for research in England
1972 Author, Paul Cuffe: Black America and the African Return Author, President Johnson's Decision to Intervene in Vietnam
1973 Author, Prohibition
1979 Author, Blue's Who's Who: A Biographical Dictionary of Blues Singers
1986 Author, I Remember: Eighty Years of Black Entertainment, Big Bands, and the Blues: An Autography
1994 Author, Factories of Death: Japanese Biological Warfare, 1932-1945, and the American Cover-Up
1996 Author,Writers Directory
2002 August 31 Died, Los Angeles, California
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Sheldon Harris consist of correspondence; photocopies of government documents; photographs; printed matter; sound recordings; video tapes; and writings relating mainly to biological warfare, especially as conducted by Japan in China before and during World War II. They include research materials used in the preparation of the book, Factories of Death: Japanese Biological Warfare, 1932-1945, and the American Cover-Up.
Sheldon Harris was one of the researchers responsible for bringing to light the facts of Japan's war crimes against humanity. The materials draw attention to atrocities committed by Japan in China between 1931 and 1945. They shed light on experiments carried out by the scientists and doctors of Unit 731 of the Japanese army by exposing human subjects to poisonous gases and infectious diseases. They also raise some controversial issues, such as an alleged immunity deal and possible cover-up between American and Japanese scientists, the question of reparation to the victims, and Japan's responsibility.
An acknowledgement of Japan's experiments with biological weapons and their use against the Chinese people came from a Japanese court shortly before Harris's death.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Biological warfare.; Sino-Japanese Conflict, 1937-1945--Biological warfare.; World War, 1939-1945--Biological warfare.; World War, 1939-1945--Japan.; United States--Military relations--Japan.; Japan--Military relations--United States.
Genre
Video tapes.; Phonotapes.
  Container List
- Federal Bureau of Investigation, 1942-1950. (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Correspondence, information sheet, memoranda, and report on biological warfare
- World War II intelligence reports, 1945 (Folder 1: 2)
- Office of Strategic Services (OSS) files index--National Archives and Records Administration (NARA) guide to RG 226, 1991 and undated. (Folder 1: 3)
  Brochure, card catalogs, list of researchers, and instructions for ordering audio-visual records
- Reports of the U. S. Naval Technical Mission to Japan, 1945-1946. (Folder 1: 4)
  Index to microfilms
- U. S. military intelligence reports
  - Japanese Biological Warfare, 1945 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Biological Warfare: Activities and Capabilities of Foreign Nations, 1946 (Folder 1: 6)
- Summary report on scientific intelligence survey in Japan--United Kingdom report on Unit 731, 1946-1947. (Folder 1: 7)
  Includes a draft report on biological research in the United States
- Japanese report on inspection by the Red Cross of prison camps in Manchuria, 1943-1945. (Folder 1: 8)
  Includes affidavits, correspondence, and printed matter relating to Japanese experiments in biological warfare in Manchuria using prisoners of war for testing
- Official German documents on biological warfare, 1941-1945. (Folder 1: 9)
  Includes list of documents and reports, including H. Kliewe intelligence report after Germany's surrender, ALSOS mission, and Hoyzo monograph, 1942-1945
- Report by George W. Merck on activities of the United States in the field of biological warfare, undated (Folder 1: 10)
- Murray Sanders
  - Biographical materials, 1961 and undated. (Folder 1: 11)
    Correspondence, press release, and miscellany
  - Report on biological warfare, 1945 (Folder 1: 12)
- Arvo T. Thompson, 1945-1946. (Folder 1: 13)
  Floor plans of Pingfan (Heibo) installation
- Herbert H. Fell--Summary report on biological warfare investigations by Edwin V. Hill and Joseph Victor, 1947 (Folder 1: 14)
- Shiro Ishii dossier, 1945-1948. (Folder 1: 15)
  Correspondence, list of papers, memoranda, and printed matter
- Stenographic transcripts of interrogation of Masaji Kitano by S. F. Whiteridge and A. H. Schvichterberg, Tokyo, and translation of statement by Kitano, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
- Investigations of Shiro Ishii, 1945-1948; 1982. (Folder 2: 3)
  Memoranda and reports. Includes an article by Peter Kalisher and a report on war crime broadcast on 60 Minutes, CBS television network
- Charles A. Willoughby files, undated. (Folder 2: 4)
  List
- Postwar biological warfare investigations, 1946-1951. (Folder 2: 5)
  Dossier, memoranda, and reports
- Cover-up documents and information on unit 100, 1941-1950. (Folder 2: 6-8)
  Includes bio-data of Murray Sanders, correspondence, interview, messages, notes, printed matter, report on the Japanese violations of the laws of war, and statement
- Japanese archive index list, 1941-1948 (Folder 2: 9)
- Dugway documents, 1944-1947. (Folder 2: 10)
  Primarily interviews relating to biological warfare
- Hospital regulations, Fort Detrick, Frederick, Maryland, 1960. (Box-folder 3: 1)
  Memorandum and report
- Letter to Charles Wilson in response to the theory of biological experiments conducted by Japan using American prisoners of war in Mukden, Manchuria, 1986 (Folder 3: 2)
- Report by N. Paul Hudson--Liaison officer, Office of the Surgeon General, 1944-1945. (Folder 3: 3)
  Concerns his responsibility for procurement and storage, and the issue of recognizing biological weapons as part of biological aspects of defense. Includes printed matter
- End of war plans, Fort Detrick, Frederick, Maryland, 1945-1947. (Folder 3: 4)
  List of requirements, memorandum, printed matter, and questionnaire
- U.S. Chemical Warfare service digitized records, dates unknown. (Folder 3: 5)
  3 compact discs
- Dugway documents from Martin Furmanski--Reports by Herbert Fell, Karl F. Meyer, R. Pollitzer, and others, 1942-2000. (Folder 3: 6)
  Includes correspondence, memoranda, and printed matter
- History of the Chemical Warfare Service in World War II, 1940-1945: Biological Warfare Research in the United States, by Rexmond C. Cochrane, 1947. (Box-folder 4: 1-2)
  Report
- Biological warfare time line from New York Times, 1937 and 1989. (Folder 4: 3)
  Research by Ted Colvin
- Soviet Biological Warfare and Chemical Warfare Preparations and Capabilities, by Walter Hirsch, 1951. (Box-folder 5: 1)
- Nuremberg trials, 1945-1946. (Folder 5: 2)
  Printed matter
- "Plague, Politics, and Policy: The Decision to Grant Immunity to Suspected Japanese Biological Warfare War Criminals," dissertation by Thomas K. Haycraft, 1999-2000. (Folder 5: 3)
  Includes a letter to Sheldon Harris
- "America's Biological Warfare Program in the Second World War," Barton J. Bernstein, 1988. (Folder 5: 4)
  Article
- "Churchill's Secret Biological Weapons," Barton J. Bernstein, and "Churchill's Anthrax Bombs: A Debate," R. V. Jones and J. M. Lewis, 1987. (Folder 5: 5)
  Articles
- "Who Knew?", 2001, undated. (Folder 5: 6)
  Article on Japanese germ warfare in China by Takao Matsumura, undated. Includes a letter to Sheldon Harris and a message about Syoji Kondo's testimony
- Articles by others on arms control, nuclear freeze, security system in Africa, and United States policy of using chemical weapons against Japan in World War II, 1984-1989 (Folder 5: 7)
- Chemical warfare in China, 1945-1993. (Box-folder 6: 1)
  Articles, clippings, correspondence, memoranda, messages, notes, outline, program, and research report
- "Japan's Secret Weapon," Barclay Moon Newman, 1944. (Folder 6: 2)
- Kharbarovsk trial--"Materials on the Trial of Former Servicemen of the Japanese Army Charged with Manufacturing and Employing Bacteriological Weapons,", 1950. (Box-folder 6: 3)
- "Biological Warfare in China: One Family's Encounter," Archie R. Crouch, undated. (Box-folder 7: 1)
  Includes brochure and press release
- "Voyage of the Death Ship: Manila to Japan," George Weller, 1945. (Folder 7: 2)
- "Japan's War from Manchuria to Hiroshima, 1931-1945: The Great Asian-Pacific Crescent of Pain," Werner Gruhl, 1999-2002. (Folder 7: 3)
  Includes a letter to Sheldon Harris, 2002; 1 photographic print depicting Werner Gruhl, 1999; and other articles and bibliography by Werner Gruhl relating to forced laborers and prisoners, and war crimes, 2001-2002
- "Hirohito: Passive, Powerless, Peace-Loving Puppet or Gung-Ho Warrior-King?" by Keith Fitzgerald, 1997-2001, undated. (Folder 7: 4)
  Includes other articles, letter, and poems by him
- "Why Hiroshima?" Edited draft writings by Davis and Paul L. Ashton, Gillespie, and Williard H. Waterous, 1985? (Box-folder 8: 1)
- "Dr. Pissedoffsky: The Letters of David Crise Cleave,", 1998-1999. (Box-folder 9: 1)
  Includes letters to Mr. and Mrs. Sheldon Harris and others
- "Three Years with the Emperor," by Sigfreid A. Schreiner, undated. (Folder 9: 2)
  Diary
- "Three Years with the Emperor," by Sigfreid A. Schreiner, undated. (Box-folder 10: 1)
- "Betrayal in High Places," by James Macay, 1996. (Folder 10: 2)
- "Allies in a Blind: Australia and the Netherlands East Indies in the Second World War," by Jack M. Ford, 1999 (Folder 10: 3)
- "Bacterial Warfare Unit and Suicide of two Physicians," by Keiichi Tsuneishi and Tomizo Asano, undated (Box-folder 11: 1)
- "The Germ Warfare Unit that Disappeared: The Kwangtung Army's 731st Unit," by Keichi Tsuneishi, translated into English, 1981. (Folder 11: 2)
  Includes related materials
- "C. Koizumi as a Promoter of the Ministry of Health and Welfare and an Originator of the BCW Research Program" and "The Research Guarded by Military Secrecy: The Isolation of the E. H. F. Virus in Japanese Biological Warfare Unit," by Keichi Tsuneishi, 1984-1986 (Folder 11: 3)
- "Satisfying the Devil's Appetite," vol. II, "The Story of the 731 Army Unit," by Seiichi Morimura, 1983. (Folder 11: 4)
  Includes excerpts from the "Devil's Paradise," Shingo Shibata
  - Correspondence, 1995-1997 (Folder 11: 5)
  - Articles and biography, 1982-1994 and undated (Folder 11: 6)
  - Miscellany, 1996-1999 (Folder 11: 7)
- Japan's National Institute of Health (JNIH) and Shingo Shibata controversies, 1987-1999. (Box-folder 12: 1)
  Article, correspondence, list of publications, map, messages, printed matter, report, schedule, statement, and miscellany
- "The Last Will and Testament of a General: Diary of General Saburo Endo," by Mainichi Shinbum, 1982. (Folder 12: 2)
  Translated into English
- Diary of Kumao Imoto--Translation by Yoshiaki Yoshimi, undated (Folder 12: 3)
- Unit 731--Special transportation documents, 1998. (Folder 12: 4)
  Letter and message
- Maps of Harbin City, China, 1980s (Folder 12: 5)
- Interviews of Japanese biological warfare veterans by Shinozuka Yoshio and Masamitsu Suzuki, 1997-1998 (Folder 12: 6)
- Translations from Japanese sources, undated. (Folder 12: 7)
  Togo Club Book (contents and excerpts); Unit 731 and the surgeons, television program; "The Sound of Earth Shaking," memoir by Ogawa Takemitsu; and "731 Menseki no Keifu," by Masakatsu Ohta. Includes a chronological table of "Unit 731 and the Germ Warfare" after World War II and related materials
- Miscellany, 1955-1998. (Folder 12: 8)
  Articles, brochures, map, and printed matter
- Chinese and Japanese documents relating to postwar memories of servicemen in Unit 731, undated. (Box-folder 13: 1-2)
  Includes chronological account of Shiro Ishii's activities from 1938-1945, bulletins of former Unit 731 members, report on Unit 731 experiments, and report on Japanese germ warfare. Also includes articles, journal, and printed matter
- Untitled pictorial bilingual Unit 731 book, undated (Folder 13: 3)
- Paul Cuffe's White Apprentice, by Sheldon Harris, 1963 (Folder 13: 4)
- "Japanese Biographical Warfare Experiments and other Atrocities in Manchuria, 1932-1945, and the Subsequent United States Cover-up: A Preliminary Assessment," by Sheldon Harris, 1991. (Box-folder 14: 1)
  Includes review of Shiro Ishii's report on Manchuria, undated
- "Japanese Biological Warfare Research on Humans: A Case Study of Microbiology and Ethics," by Sheldon Harris, undated (Folder 14: 2)
- Draft of final chapter, 1991-1996 and undated. (Folder 14: 3)
  "Biological and Toxin Weapons Research, Development and Use from the Middle Ages to 1945: A Critical Comparative Analysis," edited by Erhard Geissler and John Ellis van Courtland Moon. Includes letters to Sheldon Harris; "Japanese Biological Warfare Programs: An Overview," by Sheldon Harris and Kei'ichi Tsuneishi; and miscellaneous articles
- "Biological and Toxin Weapons Research, Development and Use from the Middle Ages to 1945: A Critical Comparative Analysis," by Erhard Geissler, 1996? (Box-folder 15: 1-2)
  Draft chapters and a letter to Sheldon Harris requesting him to review
- "Biomedical Research and Atrocities in Pre-War and World War II Japan," by Sheldon Harris, 1997-2001, undated. (Folder 15: 3-5)
  Includes draft chapter and manuscript review by Ben Garrett, and list of contents
- Reviews by Sheldon Harris and others of Stephen Endicott and Edward Hagerman, The United States and Biological Warfare: Secrets from the Early Cold War and Korea, 1999. (Folder 15: 6)
  Includes bulletins and newsletters
- Writings by Sheldon Harris and Martin Furmanski, 2000-2001
  - "Collective Amnesia: Crimes against Humanity by the Imperial Japanese Biological Weapons Program,", undated. (Folder 15: 7)
    Includes a letter to Furmanski and related materials
  - "Medical Effects of Unsophisticated Anthrax Bio-weapons: Evidence from Japanese Crimes against Humanity,", 2001
  - "Recognition of Bio-weapon Related Human Glanders Infection: Evidence from Japanese Crimes against Humanity,", 2001 (Folder 15: 8)
  - "Recognition of Crimes against Humanity Involving Bio-weapons,", 2000
  - "The Ethical Use of Data Gathered Pursuant to Crimes against Humanity,", 2001
  - "Recognition of Crimes against Humanity: Bio-weapon Events,", undated
  - Miscellany, Appendix A, letters, list of references, ethics memoranda and printed matter. Includes 1 3.5-inch computer disk containing Journal of American Medical Association articles on collective amnesia, unsophisticated anthrax weapons, and recognition of Glanders as bio-weapon, 2000-2001 and undated (Folder 15: 9)
- Writings by Sheldon Harris with Martin Furmanski for Center for Disease Control (CDC) and Emerging Infectious Diseases (EID), 1998-2002. (Box 16)
  - "The Effects of Unsophisticated Anthrax Bio-weapons I: Clinical and Pathologic Features of Victims: Evidence from Japanese Crimes against Humanity," and "The Effects of Unsophisticated Anthrax Bio-weapons I: Ethical and Scientific Justification for Publishing the Japanese Anthrax Data,", 2002? (Folder 16: 1)
    Includes correspondence
  - "The Effects of Unsophisticated Anthrax Bio-weapons II: The Pathophysiological Correlates of Aerosol Composition in Human Inhalation Anthrax," and "Effects of Unsophisticated Anthrax Bio-weapons II: Clinical and Pathologic Features of Victims Exposed to High-dose, Near-field Aerosols,", 2002. (Folder 16: 2)
    Includes related materials and minutes of meetings of American Medical Association, 1998
  - "The Effects of Unsophisticated Anthrax Bio-weapons III: The Pathophysiological Correlates of Aerosol Composition in Human Inhalation Anthrax,", 2001-2002. (Folder 16: 3)
    Includes related correspondence
  - Articles on Japanese anthrax for the Lancet, 2002 (Folder 16: 4)
- Writings by Sheldon Harris, 1991-1999, undated
  - "The American Cover-up of Japanese Human Biological Warfare Experiments, 1945-1948," by Sheldon Harris, 1998-2000? (Folder 16: 5)
    Includes letters
  - "Japanese Biological Warfare and Human Experimentation" and "Japanese Wartime Medical Atrocities," by Sheldon Harris--Chapters from "Crimes of War,", 1998-1999, undated. (Box-folder 16: 6)
    Includes letter, memoranda, printed matter, and report
  - "Japanese Biomedical Research and Atrocities during the World War II Era," by Sheldon Harris, undated (Folder 16: 7)
  - "Japanese Biological Warfare Experiments and other Atrocities in Manchuria, 1932-1945, and the Subsequent United States Cover-up: A Preliminary Assessment,", 1991 (Folder 16: 8)
- Articles, Commonweal,1969-1970, by Sheldon Harris and others, on student unrest at San Fernando Valley State College (SFVSC) (Folder 16: 9)
  - "San Fernando's Black Revolt,", 1969
  - "Meanwhile, Back in the Valley,", 1969
  - "A Landmark Decision: L.A.'s Scottsboro Boys Case,", 1970
- Frank Olson file--Frank Olson/Eric Olson Project, 1953-2001. (Folder 16: 10)
  Chronology and description of the project and printed matter
- Memorandum, 1954. (Box-folder 17: 1)
  Request for Herbert Fell report by Biological Weapons and Chemical Weapons Coordinating Committee
- John William Powell's admission of amnesty, 1945-1956. (Folder 17: 2)
  Memoranda
- Visit by Japanese group I-63 to Rocky Mountain arsenal, 1962. (Folder 17: 3)
- Korean War biological weapons allegations, 1952-1996. (Folder 17: 4)
  Intelligence report, memoranda, notes, and printed matter
- Barton J. Bernstein's letter to the president of Free Press, 1989 (Folder 17: 5)
- Military intelligence report on Korean operations, 1951-1952 (Folder 17: 6)
- Miscellaneous information on Chinese Communist 40 Army (Mukden Unit) and American prisoners of war, 1951-1959. (Folder 17: 7)
  Letter, memoranda, and printed matter
- Summary of major events and problems--United States Army Chemical Corps, 1962. (Folder 17: 8)
- Operation Whitecoat, undated. (Folder 17: 9)
  Article, fact sheet, letter, printed matter, and report
- United States army activity in the United States biological warfare programs--Report, 1977. (Folder 17: 10)
  Includes chronological summary of the U.S. Army Chemical Corps, Ohio State University contract volunteer studies, and table of extra-Mural medical research contracts, undated
- Modern continuing cover-up documents, 1986-1991. (Folder 17: 11)
- Chemical Warfare/Chemical-Biological Defense Information Analysis Center (CBIAC) literature search, 2001. (Folder 17: 12)
- Articles by others on yellow rain in Southeast Asia and Sverdlovsk anthrax outbreak of 1979, 1990-1994 (Folder 17: 13)
- Fort Detrick, Maryland--Public controversies, 1989-2001. (Folder 17: 14)
  Messages and printed matter
- Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) and Army correspondence with Sheldon Harris, 1988-1989 (Folder 17: 15)
- History of Dugway Proving Ground, 1989 and undated. (Folder 17: 16)
  Includes a letter from Sheldon Harris to the commander, 1989
- Betty Metz anthrax lawsuit, 1963-1989. (Folder 17: 17)
  Comments, correspondence, court documents, notes, printed matter, statement, and summary
- Japanese medical ethics, 1993-1996 and undated. (Box-folder 18: 1)
  Correspondence, printed matter, and report
- U. S. medical ethics, 1951-1993. (Folder 18: 2)
  Clipping, letter, notes, and printed matter
- Printed matter on biological warfare, 1959-1989 (Folder 18: 3)
- News stories
  - 1981-2001. (Folder 18: 4)
    Includes articles and a message to Sheldon Harris
  - 1992-2001. (Folder 18: 5)
    Includes clipping, message, press release, and printed matter
- Cologne fall meeting, Cologne Institute of Genetics, 1988. (Folder 18: 6)
  Announcement, clippings, correspondence, memoranda, notes, organization of Camp 731, printed matter, and schedule. Includes a paper presented by Sheldon Harris, "Japanese Biological Warfare Experiments and other Atrocities in Manchuria, 1932-1945, and the Subsequent United States Cover Up"
- Meeting--Herbin City, China, 1991. (Folder 18: 7)
  Article, correspondence, and miscellany
- Letter of invitation to Sheldon Harris, International Citizens' Forum on War Crimes and Redress, Tokyo, 1999. (Folder 18: 8)
  Letters, message, printed matter, and schedule. Includes his paper, "Japanese Medical Atrocities in World War II: Unit 731 was not an Isolated Aberration." Also includes letter from Sheldon Harris to the judges of the Tokyo District Court relating to the lawsuit of Shibata Shingo and others against Japan National Institute for Infectious Disease (JNIID)
- "The Forgotten Holocaust," symposium in honor of the fiftieth anniversary of the end of war in the Pacific, California State University, Fresno, 1995. (Folder 18: 9)
  Brochure, clipping, note, printed matter, remarks, and reviews
- "War Crimes Trials," symposium, Nimitz Museum, Texas, 1996. (Folder 18: 10)
  Brochure, letter, printed matter, schedule of events, and miscellany
- Nuremberg conference, Washington, D.C., 1996. (Box-folder 19: 1)
  Brochure, correspondence, itinerary, list of speakers, notes, printed matter, speech by Sheldon Harris on Holocaust, and related materials. Also includes an information kit about United States Holocaust Memorial Museum
- Meeting and panel discussion on Holocaust, New York, 1998. (Folder 19: 2)
  Articles and magazine
- Greater Vancouver--Japanese Canadian Citizens' Association meeting on human rights, 1998. (Folder 19: 3)
  Brochure, bulletin, and printed matter
- Changchun conference, 1998. (Folder 19: 4)
  List of attendees, letter, notes, printed matter, and related materials